Today's דף Daf is דף ל Daf Lamed and we start at
the bottom of כ"ח עמוד ב Chaf Chet Amud Bet
and with ששיסא, Sheshisa, three lines down from the wide lines beginning
of the line, dealing still with various items and their use in
an עירוב תחומין. Eiruv Techumin. Again עירוב חצירות Eiruv Chatzeiros requires bread,
this is their use in an עירוב תחומין. Eiruv Techumin. It can
be any types of foods that are good for two meals. So
ששיסא, Sheshisa, what's the story with ששיסא? Sheshisa? So that's a type
of a thing that they would make with like roasted grain and
honey and so on and it would be like, you know, some
type of a food, sweet food. So how much of it? Presumably
there's no question that that can be used, it's definitely something people
eat. So how much of it? אמר רב אחא בר פנחס תרי
סרנושי, Amar Rav Acha bar Pinchas Trei Sargushi, two like scoops full
of that, whatever that is. קיסוני, Kisoni, how about קיסוני, Kisoni, which
is roast grain but without this whole mixture? אמר אביי תרי בוני
דפומבדיתא, Amar Abaye Trei Bunei De-Pumbedisa, two measures of פומבדיתא, Pumbedisa, whatever
those measures were. אמר אביי אמרה לי אם, Amar Abaye Amra Li
Em, my mother said to me, which wasn't really his mother, it
was his nursemaid, his mother died, but he refers to his nursemaid
as his mother, thank you so much.
Stepmom? Sort of, yeah,
not stepmother in the sense that his father married her, you know,
sort of I mean it was his nursemaid but I mean not
nursemaid in the literal sense, it's whatever the nanny, but it was
the one who raised him,
okay. הני קיסוני מעלי לליבא, Hanei Kisoni Ma'ali Le-Libba, these קיסוני Kisoni
are these like roasted wheat roasted grain is good for the heart
ומבטלי מחשבתא U-Mevatli Machshavta and gets rid of bad thoughts, like you
know, puts your mind at ease. ואמר אביי אמרה לי אם, Ve-Amar
Abaye Amra Li Em, and אביי Abaye said,
my mother said to me, I'm sorry did I just read myself
complete myself, ואמר אביי אמרה לי אם האי מאן דאית ליה חושא
דליבא, Ve-Amar Abaye Amra Li Em Hai Man De-Isei Chusha De-Libba, somebody
who has like weakness of the heart, ליתי בישרא דאטמא ימינא דדיכרא,
Leisei Bistra De-Atma Yamina De-Dikra,
get meat from the right side of an animal of a ram,
וליתי קיבויי דרעיא דניסן U-Leisei Kivuyei De-Re'isa De-Nissan
and get sort of like the dried dung of the grazing animals
during ניסן, Nissan, and you're going to you're going to use that
to make a fire, ואי ליכא קיבויי דרעיא Ve-Ei Leika Kivuyei De-Re'isa
and if you don't have that, ליתי סוגייני דערבתא, Leisei Sugyani De-Arvatha,
get you know basically wood what's it called twigs of willow and
ונכפיה Ve-Nikhpei
and burn them, you know make these into charcoal either these wood
either these wood chips or the buffalo chips as they're called, וניכול
Ve-Neichol
and you know and roast the meat over it, וניכול Ve-Neichol and
then eat this meat that you've roasted over it, ונישתי בתריה חמרא
מרקא Ve-Nishti Basrei Chamra Marka and drink after it wine, מרקא Marka
and drink after it mixed wine, and that'll solve all your medical
problems. Okay אביי Abaye very often would quote his אם Em the
woman who raised him as in these medical health issues. All right,
back to back to the amounts you need for עירוב תחומין. Eiruv
Techumin. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, we're
now five lines from the bottom, כל שהוא לפתן כדי לאכול בו,
Kol She-Hu Liftan Kedei Le-Echol Bo, כל שאינו לפתן כדי לאכול הימנו.
Kol She-Eino Liftan Kedei Le-Echol Mimenu.
Similar to what we said yesterday, anything that is a condiment then
it's the amount of that condiment that you would eat you would
use during two meals, so כדי לאכול בו Kedei Le-Echol Bo to
eat two meals with it, you know, so not out of it,
not that you're going to you know eat two meals of I
don't know peanut butter straight, but you're going to use peanut butter
in your two meals, like you know as a peanut butter sandwich.
If it's not a condiment then כדי לאכול הימנו, Kedei Le-Echol Mimenu,
how much of that would you eat straight to fill you up
for two meals. So a little ironically something that is less of
a staple, less central to the meal you need less of to
count as two meals' worth for עירוב תחומין, Eiruv Techumin, like we
learned the other day if you have a little vinegar it's the
amount of vinegar you would put on your salad and it's not
actually that you would eat the vinegar straight according to one opinion
it would even be of a side salad even if your main
meal wasn't the salad. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says now
we're going to talk about where certain things fall in, בשר חי,
Basar Chai, raw meat.
Now raw meat could be a perfect example of something you couldn't
make an עירוב Eiruv out of who eats raw meat? But we'll
see that the גמרא Gemara actually will discuss it a little bit
in a bit, but here it's assuming that בשר חי Basar Chai
you could eat it. So כדי לאכול הימנו, Kedei Le-Echol Mimenu,
but that would be and that would be the amount that you
would eat of it straight so it's assuming not only would you
eat raw meat but you wouldn't even eat it as some type
of thing to go on your bread, you'd eat it straight. Again
it's really quite strange I don't know how many people are eating
raw meat. So כדי לאכול הימנו. Kedei Le-Echol Mimenu. בשר צלוי, Basar
Tzelui,
if it's roasted meat, then רבה אמר כדי לאכול בו, Rabba Amar
Kedei Le-Echol Bo,
roasted meat ah that you don't eat straight that you just eat
like on bread. So that according to רבה, Rabba, so it's only
the amount. Now that you would eat with it of the meal
together with that amount, רב יוסף אמר Rav Yosef amar כדי לאכול
הימנו. kedei l'echol heimenu. No, roasted meat you would eat straight. אמר
רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef מנא מינא לה, mina mina la, where
do I know this from? דהא פרסאי, deha parsa'ei,
because the Persians אכלי תבחיקי, achlei tavhikei,
they eat תבחיקי tavhikei which is like chunks of meat and presumably
roasted meat, בלא נהמא belo nahama
without bread. So you see that this is not something that just
is a condiment for bread, but it's something that you eat straight.
אמר ליה אביי, Amar leh Abaye, ופרסאי הוי רובא דעלמא? uparsai havei
ruba de'alma?
Similar to discussions before about how do you dictate in terms of
for some people do it, does that dictate for everyone? So are
Persians the majority of the world? ותנן Vatnan and I'll show you
that normally we don't just take a subgroup and define it for
everyone. בגדי עניים לעניים, Bigdei ani'im la'ani'im,
clothes used for poor people is
determines, meaning the size of what's a minimum size of clothing for
poor people we say is three finger widths by three finger widths.
So those are considered to be clothes if they're the types of
size that poor people would use, and for poor people they are
considered garments and they can become טמא tamei even if they're just
three finger widths by three finger widths. בגדי
עשירים, Bigdei ashirim, but clothes that normally the size that normally rich
people
would be prepared to wear, which is bigger, three טפחים tefachim by
three טפחים, tefachim, maybe you could use it as a scarf, anything
less they would throw out. So that's לעשירים, la'ashirim, that's clothes for
rich people. אבל, Aval, top of ל lamed עמוד א, amud alef,
אבל בגדי
עשירים לעניים לא. aval bigdei ashirim la'ani'im lo.
But the size for rich people, the three טפחים tefachim by three
טפחים, tefachim, you don't need that for poor people. Poor people, meaning
the short version is that for poor people the size of what
constitutes clothing is smaller than for rich people because they'll use things
as they'll be more willing to first of all wear use things
as patches and use smaller pieces of clothing. So for poor people
the size is smaller and therefore when the question is if something
טמא tamei touches a piece of clothing, is it still considered a
בגד beged to become טמא? tamei? The answer is different if it's
owned by a poor person or if it's owned by a rich
person, whether it's considered clothing. So you see that you don't say,
ah, since for poor people that's considered clothing it's going to be
considered clothing for everybody. So you don't go by, you take a
subset, you look at each group by itself. So maybe if we're
asking a הלכה halacha whether for Persians is this what's the הלכה,
halacha, that's one thing. But don't look at Persians and have that
subset dictate for everyone.
And sometimes we did say that didn't even work for them.
I know, I'll get to you in a minute. וכי תימא הכא
לחומרא והכא לחומרא, Vechi teima hacha lechumra vehacha lechumra, maybe it should
depend, maybe whether we go by the subset or not depends on
the question of is it stringent or lenient. So when it comes
to the idea
that, one minute,
right, one minute, how's it work?
Right. So for the poor people we're only consider it a,
it's a little strange, it's not really a חומרא. chumra. A real
חומרא chumra would be that if for the rich
people you would consider it to be a בגד beged even if
it was the size
for small people, for poor people. But even for poor people we
are considering it to be a, we're
going by the smaller size, and that's being stringent for them. So
here though, what's the argument? Here the question is do we consider
roast meat a condiment or a main meal? And if we consider
it a main meal not a condiment, then again ironically you need
more of it. So here what we wanted to say is, well,
at least let's look at what the Persians do and they have
it as a main meal and therefore you should need more of
it. Okay, so at least that's going, hold on let me just
double check.
Yeah, explain the חומרא. chumra. They say the חומרא chumra for the
poor, for the what poor people they don't give them the allowance
they give to the wealthy people.
They don't give them the
allowance of a בגד beged that's larger?
Right, it's a חומרא chumra that you go by the smaller size.
Right,
but it's only a חומרא chumra for the small people. You don't
use the smaller size for the rich people. You're only using the
smaller size for the poor people. So you're only using the more
מחמיר machmir
criteria for the group that it's relevant for.
Hold on let me just double check. דתתא הויא ליפטר לכולי עלמא
ליבעי שיעורא רבא. datata havya liftur lekulei alma libei shiura raba. Yeah,
it's not exactly parallel. By the case by
the poor, it's since for the poor people it's
a בגד beged for them we should use the criteria that's relevant
for them. And here what the גמרא Gemara seems to be arguing
is that let's consider it to be a main meal for everybody,
not just for the Persians. It's not really parallel. The way רש״י
Rashi frames it, והכא לחומרא, vehacha lachumra, four lines from the top,
דאזא הוה לפתא לכולי עלמא לבעי שיעור רבא. deaza hava lifta lechulei
alma libei shiur raba. But he maybe the point is like what
you assume is your default. Why don't we assume as default something
is considered to be a main meal and therefore until for everybody
it is considered a condiment then it should remain in the default
status of a main meal. All right, so the fact
that
for
at least some people,
all right,
it's interesting, but anyway maybe we should use sort of you know
we should we should go by right
so again it is strange because presumably again in the case of
the rich and the poor you're using each group's each group's criteria
that's relevant for it. Here you're trying to determine a universal standard.
So the גמרא Gemara says okay but maybe we should just be
מחמיר machmir here and take the bigger standard. ותניא veatanya but we
taught in the ברייתא Baraita רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר מערבין לחולה
ולזקן כדי מזונו ולרבתן בסעודה בינונית של כל אדם. Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar omer maarvin lacholeh ulazaken kedei mezono velaravtan biseudah beinonit shel kol
adam. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that in terms of how
much if it's somebody that is ill or elderly and they don't
eat as much so you do what's two meals for them. But
this is not exactly parallel if it's somebody that is a you
know gluttonous or starving then you don't use it for him a
large meal then you do an average meal. So it's interesting that's
the exact opposite you use the subjective standard when it's a קולא
kula and not when it's a חומרא. chumra. Right, so for somebody
doesn't eat as much you go less than the standard two meals
but somebody that normally eats more you stop yourself at the standard's
two meals.
What if you're making this for a group of people and one's
rich and one's poor? What? What if you've got a group of
people that you're making this for?
Well each person needs a separate עירוב eiruv though so yeah. Well
when you're doing עירובי תחומין eiruvei techumin you know וכל החצרות vechol
hatzerot etc.
How likely is a חולה choleh and a זקן zaken going to
travel 2000 אמות?
amot? It's a good question. I don't know maybe as people help
them. Or go that far. Yeah it's true 2000 אמות amot is
right is like is like three fifths of a mile it's a
kilometer.
In 24 25 hours.
Right right you take a very long walk. A long walk. All
you have to be is a חולה מעיים choleh meayim you just
have to have like a stomach you know right you don't have
to be חולה choleh all body. Anyway so anyway so the גמרא
Gemara says so you see that that at least according to רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar we use a subjective standard
to be lenient. So the גמרא Gemara says okay קשיא kashya that's
difficult. So again I really have to tell you that it's not
clear to me because in the case of the עני oni and
the עשיר ashir you were using each group's subjective standard according to
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon you're using each you're using the קולא kula
subjective standard of a subgroup for that subgroup and according to the
issue about the meat the גמרא Gemara was just saying that you
don't use the more מחמיר machmer standard of the Persians for the
group that it's not relevant for. So that's incredibly consistent that you
use each group's specific standard. So anyway it's not exactly clear to
me how the גמרא's Gemara lining all of that up. I would
also say it's quite bizarre that the גמרא Gemara takes it for
granted that raw meat you would eat straight and the only question
is whether roast meat you would eat on a sandwich.
So I don't know how you're going to eat raw meat if
you're going to anyway eat it straight. And the final point that
Michael raises that it is true the גמרא Gemara raised before that
whole issue about
whether
stuff was considered to be whether you go by in places where
they eat it or do they use it as animal food and
so on. Again there could be a difference whether the question is
whether it's considered food or not human food or animal food and
there maybe we look at a complete universal standard. Here the question
was more what way is it eaten maybe here we would look
more at the more subjective or the more local standards. Anyway. What?
It's tartare is basically raw meat.
How many people eat that though?
And I mean and if you're going to eat it how many
people eat it straight?
That's what I actually think you do.
You eat it straight?
It's a very expensive...
No one in America when I was growing up ever ate raw
fish. Yeah and now we serve it at קידושים. kiddushes.
Right.
All right. I don't know what to say. Maybe anyway so let's
take a look. The גמרא Gemara in the end will question the
raw meat.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this same
thing about did you have a question on הני פרסאי רובא דעלמא
הוו? hanai parsayi ruba dealma havu? I mean there probably wasn't an
awareness, we often don't have the awareness ourselves that there are you
know cultures larger than ours that eat things that we would never
even dream of eating. Yeah right. Dogs and cats.
Right there's a scandal right now in Europe that they're using dog
and cat meat now in... really? Yeah it was a crazy story.
But but you know in East Asia this is a common a
fairly common food. Right and there are more of them than there
are of us.
That's true. So maybe they are רובא דעלמא ruba dealma for... that's
true. Okay yes.
That a localized custom even if prevalent but not majority of the
world can potentially carry the day or not? Like you know so
what do you say then? Well let's say exactly that let's say
in America we eat whatever it is but you know someone says
they don't so... ...and the majority of the world...
Yes, so that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not clear about.
This is the first time we've seen that there's different standards for
different people, right? The עניים aniyim, *aniyim* and the עשירים ashirim, *ashirim*.
Right, right. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does, so again, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* at the beginning of the פרק
*perek* tries to work that out. When do we sort of look
at one universal standard, when do we look at each region with
its own standard? It's very, it's not a clear consensus about that,
but the logical thing to do is if you have a clear,
you know, that if different regions are different, you would go by
regional standards, and if there's something that's clearly a universal, you know,
majority, then maybe you would go by that. But the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*, you know, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here is just rejecting using
the Persian standard for non-Persians, which is a reasonable position. Okay, but
how that relates to the עניים *aniyim* and the עשירים *ashirim* case
is a little, you know, is, or no, it is similar to
the עניים *aniyim* and the עשירים *ashirim* that each group goes by
its own standard. What doesn't make sense is the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
sort of חומרא *chumra* קולא *kula* type of a framing as a
קשיא *kashya*. But let's say I'm sick
and, you know, I can't
even eat this at all. Well, that's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon.
*Rabbi Shimon* says. Let's say I'm lactose intolerant and I can't even
eat this at all.
So that's like the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about תרומה t'ruma *Terumah*. So
you are right, there's different issues and we'll talk about that later
when we get to the place about accessibility. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says in terms of whether you can eat the particular food,
there as long as it's edible by some people, but you're right,
it's a little ironic that it's enough that it's edible by someone
else, but the amount would be the amount that how much of
it I would eat. So let's say תרומה trumah. *Terumah* for a
ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael*, so we'd say oh, it's considered food because a
כהן kohen *Kohen* would eat it, but עם ישראל *Am Yisrael* I
can't eat it, but suppose I also have a stomach issue, so
it's a less amount for me even though I can't eat the
food because it's only edible by a כהן kohen. *Kohen*, so it
is a little bit strange that by that you do measure by
others. But at least here the point seems to be you go
by the subgroup and in רבי Rebbi, שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*'s statement it's
not even a subgroup, it's the particular individual which is even more
of a חידוש chiddush. *chiddush*. Okay, and that anyway is consistent with
the עניים *aniyim* and the עשירים *ashirim* idea that you go by
the particular subgroup. Yes.
Star K says in the website they go by local standards for
בישול עכו"ם *bishul akum*.
Okay, good to know. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. Okay, ומי אמר *U'mi amar*, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
קשיא *kashya*. So that's difficult that that makes it hard to say
that there's an issue about the, you know, the חומרא *chumra* issue
is playing out because in רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* you're going לקולא le'kula *l'kula*. והתניא *Ve'hatanya*
says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, ומי אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar הכי *u'mi amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar hachi*? Did
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar*
really say that, that you could be lenient for the חול *chol*
and the זקן zaken *zaken*, or that you're more subjective? And again,
that's not even a group, that's an individual. והתניא *Ve'hatanya* that we
teach in a ברייתא braita *Baraisa*, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar אומר *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer* עוג מלך הבשן Og
Melech Habashan. *Og Melech ha'Bashan* פתחו כמלואו *pitcho k'milo'o*. There's a הלכה
halacha. *halacha* that if you have a מת *meis* in a house,
okay, obviously everything under the roof is טמא tamei. *tamei*. But imagine
that you have various doors and the doors have like awnings over
them. So if the door was open, the טומאה *tumah* would go
out of the door under the awning, right, that's outside of the
door. But you have like multiple exits in your house. Now normally
you would imagine until I've opened a door I'm safe, but actually
the הלכה *halacha* is, there's a הלכה *halacha* called סוף טומאה לצאת
*sof tumah latzes*, that the exit through which you're eventually going to
bring the dead body, it's considered like that door's already open and
the טומאה *tumah* is already gone out there. Okay, but in a
way it's good that you know that there's a specific exit because
if there's no particular exit that you know which one it's going
to go out of, then you apply it to all the exits.
This idea that it's like the טומאה *tumah* has gone out of
it. Is this דרבנן derabbanan *de'rabbanan*? Is it הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha
le'Moshe mi'Sinai*? That he was no longer טמא tamei. *tamei*?
What?
The room and the exit.
And the exit. And the exit. But if it's a particular one,
then it's only the exit it's going to go out. So the
question is what's considered to be a minimum size that this thing
can be considered a doorway that you're going to bring the מת
*meis* out of. So, so רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rebbi Shimon ben
Elazar *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* says if you have in your house
a dead עוג מלך הבשן Og Melech Habashan *Og Melech ha'Bashan*, like
Jack the Giant Slayer the movie, so you have a dead giant
in your house. Okay, so פתחו כמלואו *pitcho k'milo'o*. If you want
to say I'm going to bring him out of that door and
therefore only that door is טמא *tamei* and not the other exit,
it has to be a door that's, that's big enough to get
him out. Okay, so if it's just a normal size exit even
though it counts for other people, then that would, then that would
not be considered the, his exit way and it would not save
the other exit. The טומאה *tumah* is always difficult,
let me ask a question for טומאה *tumah*.
טומאה *tumah*, alright anyway we'll see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says.
ואביי *Ve'Abaye* and אביי *Abaye* would say back, anyway you see here
that he is a does a, you know, takes a more... so
again, what's the problem? It's, you know, there also it's subjective. But
what we're doing is we're challenging the, the, the lenient position at
the end that he says that if somebody is more hungry, you
know, that you basically you go leniently. If somebody needs less, you
do less. But if somebody is a is starving, you still limit
yourself to the standard of two meals. So here too the question
is so why don't we just say that you don't go beyond,
you know, the standard? So the standard size of a door you
wouldn't demand more than that. ואביי *Ve'Abaye*, so אביי *Abaye* will say
back, התם היכי ליעבד *hasam heichi liyaved*? What do you want to
do in that case? הדומיי נהדמיה ונפיק *hadumei nahadmeih ve'nafik*? You want
to chop him up into pieces and take him out? So therefore...
For which is funny because, I mean I guess he's saying that
a starving person could still make do by less than two meals,
but he's just saying there it is not, you know, it's no
way you can call it a door if he can't fit out.
So it's a different case, you can't bring a relevance from here.
But here we could still go by a standard size of two
meals. Okay, so what do we have now? We have the idea
that we have this interesting statement of רבי Rebbi שמעון בן אלעזר
that you can go by the subjective reality of how much a
person can eat to be מיקל, meikel, but you won't go more
than the standard of two meals. And here again, it's more than
some issues we were saying before about a sub-group, here it's just
particular individuals. So the גמרא Gemara, says: איבעיא להו. ibaya lehu. They
raise the question: פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי שמעון בן אלעזר או לא?
peligi rabbanan alei de'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar o lo? Do the רבנן
Rabbanan argue on him or not? תא שמע. ta shema. Come and
hear: דאמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן. de'amar Rabbah bar
bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan. עוג מלך הבשן. Og Melech Habashan, Now
this is רבי Rebbi. שמעון בן אלעזר not by the עירוב, eiruv,
but by עוג מלך הבשן Og Melech Habashan case. So רבה בר
בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana says in the name of רבי
יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: עוג מלך הבשן פתחו בארבע. Og Melech Habashan pitcho
b'arba. You go by בארבע b'arba טפחים tefachim like you would normally,
that would be the normal size of a door of a normal
person. So even by עוג מלך הבשן, you go by the standard.
So the גמרא Gemara, says: התם דאיכא פתחים טובא. hasam de'ika petachim
tuvei. The גמרא Gemara says
that's not necessarily a counter-proof of רבי שמעון. That might be that
you would choose the ארבעה טפחים arba'ah tefachim opening to designate as
his one over the other ones. That there's a lot of openings:
דאיכא חד דהוה ארבעה, de'ika chad de'hava arba'ah, and there's one that's
ארבעה. arba'ah. דבוודאי כי קא מרווח, de'vada'ei ki ka marvach,
you're going to have to broaden one of the openings. So isn't
anybody trying to by the way figure out how he got in
the house?
You built the house around him, I guess. I don't know, whatever.
Anyway, if you're going to make one of them bigger: בהוא קא
מרווח, behu ka marvach, you're going to make the one that's already
ארבעה טפחים arba'ah tefachim bigger. But that so but if they're all
ארבעה טפחים, arba'ah tefachim, then you know and you just designate one,
that would not be enough because none of them is really considered
to be an appropriate opening in the size that it is. So
they might agree to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר and say that unless
it's his size, it's not an appropriate opening.
Unless it's the only one that's ארבעה טפחים arba'ah tefachim and עוג
מלך הבשן is in and then what would you say is the
one.
If there's one that's ארבעה טפחים arba'ah tefachim and others that are
less, then even רבי שמעון בן אלעזר might agree that not that
that this is going to be the opening that's going to be
expanded for him and you can designate it as the opening. But
if they're all less than if they're all ארבעה טפחים, arba'ah tefachim,
then even if you designate one, that might not count as his
opening because there's nothing that's fit for being an opening because it's
not the right size. And then they're all טמא. Then they're all
טמא.
So how come we don't say דהוה דבר למפרע, de'hava davar l'mafrea,
that that's the one that you were you know.
So let's see we say that. Yeah, we don't say that here.
Okay, I mean it's a special תרומה truma הלכה. Okay. אמר רב
חייא
בר אבא אמר רב: amar Rav Chiya bar Abba amar Rav: מערבין
בבשר חי. me'arvin be'basar chai. Now going back to the raw meat,
where finally there's going to be debate about it because it's bizarre
the גמרא Gemara just took it for granted. Anyway, so this is
the first of the things, you can use raw meat.
אמר רב שימי בר חייא: amar Rav Shimi bar Chiya: מערבין בביצים
חיות. me'arvin be'veitzim chayot. You can do raw eggs. I don't know,
ask me, more people eat raw eggs than they eat raw meat.
וכמה? ve'kama? And how much? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק: amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak: סיני אמר. Sinai amar. סיני, Sinai, which was a
name for רב יוסף Rav Yosef because it means like somebody that
like is a בקי baki and knows everything. He said it also.
He says: שתיים, shtayim, two raw eggs. So presumably one raw egg
per meal. Alright, so anyway, so there it was interesting that you
raw meat and raw eggs count. But what's particularly interesting is this
question about subjective standards. And again, you have three possibilities: you only
go by one universal size for everyone, each region is separate, or
sub-group עניים, עשירים, פרסיים, parsi'im, other people. Or רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
is that at least לקולא for the quantity says you even go
by the individual. And you know, the point that Michael made is
a correct one, that for to even within the very same עירוב
eiruv you're placing, you could look at that answer differently. So is
it fit for eating? It might be enough that it's fit for
somebody else to eat. How much of it might be how much
of it I would eat? Right? Is it considered to be the
other issue we were talking about is it considered to be the
main course or is it considered to be a condiment? So that
might go by yet a third standard. So it's quite strange about
which of these standards you apply in terms of you know some
universal or some subjective standard. Okay, now we move on to an
to another point in the משנה, Mishna, which is out of עירוב
eiruv and by נדרים. nedarim. That if somebody makes a נדר neder
not to have מזון, mazon, food. But it doesn't say אוכל ochel
though, food. מזון mazon is more like satiating food. Then he can
have water and salt. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: הנודר
מן המזון. ha'noder min hamazon. So מלח ומים, melach u'mayim, water and
salt: הוא דלא איקרי מזון, hu de'la ikri mazon, that's not called
מזון. mazon. הכול מילי איקרי מזון, hakol milei ikri mazon, this seems
that everything else, fruits and vegetables or whatever, are called מזון, mazon,
not just אוכל ochel but מזון. mazon. לימא תיהוי תיובתא דרב ושמואל?
leima tehei tiyuva de'Rav u'Shmuel? Let this let this should be a
contradiction of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. דאמרי תרוייהו, de'amri tarveihu, that
they both say: אין מברכין בורא מיני מזונות אלא על חמשת המינים
בלבד. ein me'varchin borei minei mezonot ela al chameshet haminim bilvad. That
you only say בורא מיני מזונות borei minei mezonot on the חמשת
המינים chameshet haminim and not on things like rice. So this should
be a challenge to them. Now of course the obvious question is,
but everybody agrees you don't say בורא מיני מזונות borei minei mezonot
on fruits and vegetables. The whole debate was like do you say
it on
rice. The מציאות metzius is, is that some people talk about, you
know, other locations in the Far East, right, where rice is like
the staple, right? You sometimes had a little vegetables or a little
meat or whatever. So nobody disagrees to the מציאות metzius that people
make a meal on rice. But what's so if you're going to
say you can't make a בורא מיני מזונות Borei Minei Mezonos on
rice, that's because you're going to be a pure formalist, and you're
going to say even if people make a meal, I'm not going
to be prepared to call it מזון, mazon, מזונות, mezonos, I only
call that to
the חמשת המינים. chameshes haminim. Okay, so you're a pure formalist. If
you're willing to call rice מזון, mazon, you're not such a formalist.
You say, you know, you look at the מציאות metzius about how
it's used and so on. So if that's true, you could understand
that for נדר neder purposes, you know, מזון mazon has a broader
sense of anything that sort of fills you in any way. But
the real question is on רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel because if
they're such formalists that nothing is מזון mazon other than the חמשת
המינים, chameshes haminim, then how could this משנה Mishnah make it all
set? Because they always go by very formal criteria. So the גמרא
Gemara says, ולא סבינהו חד זימנא? ve-lo savinhu chad zimna?
Okay, but we've already in ברכות Berachos contradicted them otherwise. So what's
fine? So you contradict them here too. So the גמרא Gemara says,
no, לימא תיהוי תיובתא נמי מהא. leimei teivtei tiyuvta nami me-ha. We
want to know just for the record whether this משנה Mishnah is
also a contradiction to their position, because their position again is pure
a very formal formalist position that only חמשת המינים chameshes haminim can
be called מזון, mazon, and our משנה Mishnah says that for נדר
neder purposes, any almost anything can be מזון. mazon. So אמר רב
הונא באומר כל הזן עלי. amar Rav Huna be-omer kol ha-zan alai.
Here's a difference. Although the משנה Mishnah says הנודר מן המזון, ha-nodeir
min ha-mazon, it's really imprecise. You didn't say you didn't say all
מזון mazon is forbidden, you say anything that is זן, zan, that
provides sustenance. So there's a difference between calling it מזון, mazon, which
has a sense like it's a staple, and הזן ha-zan means one
of the things it does is it fills you, but it's not
a filler. Okay, there's a difference between calling something a it's the
wrong word, but calling something like a filler, which means that's its
primary identity, and something that fills you somewhat. So any so that's
the משנה Mishnah which says anything that that fills you to some
degree. And therefore it is more broad than the word מזון. mazon.
מיא ומלחא הוא דלא זייני הא כל מילי זייני? maya u-mivcha hu
de-lo zaini ha kol mili zaini? So the גמרא Gemara now challenges
that. מיא ומלחא הוא דלא זייני הא כל מילי זייני? maya u-mivcha
hu de-lo zaini ha kol mili zaini? So would you say that
it's only water and salt that don't fill, everything else does fill
you
up? Or not fully fill you up, but whatever, provide sustenance? ואמר
רבה בר בר חנה כי הוינא אזלינן בתריה דרבי יוחנן. ve-amar Rabbah
bar bar Chana ki havina azlinan basrei de-Rabbi Yochanan. He said when
I was following רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan למיכל פירות גינוסר, le-meichal peiros
Ginosar, that this we had the same גמרא Gemara in ברכות, Berachos,
to eat from the fruit of גינוסר Ginosar in ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. So it was so delicious, וכי הוינא בי מאה, ve-ki havina
bei mea, when there were a hundred of us, הוי מנקטינן לכל
חד וחד עשרה עשרה. hava minkatinan le-chol chad ve-chad asara asara. Everyone
would was like pick ten fruits to eat. כי הוינא בי עשרה,
ki havina bei asara, and when ten of us went on this
little expedition, הוי מנקטינן לכל חד וחד מאה מאה. hava minkatinan le-chol
chad ve-chad mea mea. Everyone would gather a hundred. I don't get
it, like maybe they were given a thousand as an allowance or
something. But anyway, okay, so we would go and pick all of
these fruits of גינוסר. Ginosar. וכל מאה מינייהו הוה מחזיק להו צנא
בת תלתא סאוי. ve-kol mea mineihu hava machzik le-hu tzana bas tlata
sa-ei. And, you know, every hundred of them either wouldn't fill or
would fill a huge bucket like or whatever the size of three
סאה, se'ah, which is a very large amount.
והוה אכיל להו כולהו. ve-hava achil le-hu kulhu. We would eat all
of these, these hundred fruits, ואמר שבועה דלא טעימנא זיזונא ve-amar shvua
de-lo taiyamna zizuna
and, you know, and we would say that שבועה, shvua, excuse me,
a שבועה shvua that I have not tasted enough to fill me,
meaning this they'd be totally delicious and they would be non-filling. So
here you see, what?
Chinese food, right, exactly. So anyway, so the point being that, you
know, that not everything gives you a sense of being sated or
being filled. Of course, the obvious answer could be there's a little
bit of an exaggeration, one gets a sense by the whole thing.
But anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara answer is. So אמר
רב הונא אמר רב amar Rav Huna amar Rav sorry, is that
an answer?
One minute. ואמר שבועה דלא טעימנא זיזונא. ve-amar shvua de-lo taiyamna zizuna.
אימא מזונא. eima mazona. Ah, no, it's not again the difference between
זיזונא zizuna provide me some sense of being sated and מזונא mazona
which is like a staple, which is something that's much more central
to its identity. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says for בורא מיני
מזונות, Borei Minei Mezonos, it's חמשת המינים chameshes haminim according to רב
Rav and שמואל Shmuel or it includes אורז ודוחן. orez ve-dochan. Our
משנה Mishnah that's broader is not because we're labeling it מזון, mazon,
which means that the thing is a real like staple, but we're
calling it זן, zan, it provides filling. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
goes on.
Since we mentioned a שבועה shevuah and we're talking about נדר, neder,
we're going to talk about another שבועה. shevuah. אמר רב הונא אמר
רב: Amar Rav Huna Amar Rav: שבועה
שלא אוכל כיכר זו. shevuah shelo ochel kikar zo. If somebody takes
an oath that I won't eat this loaf of bread, מערבין לו
בה, mearvin lo bah, you can use it for an עירוב. eiruv.
כיכר זו עלי, kikar zo alai, if this loaf of bread is
forbidden to me, אין מערבין לו בה, ein mearvin lo bah, you
cannot use it for an עירוב. eiruv. Now what is the difference
between those two?
So רש״י Rashi says that the difference is, is that the first
case you say I won't eat. So eat, but you can use
it for—first of all other people can eat it. So, and we
know if other people can eat it, that's okay. So fine, so
you can't eat it, other people can, you can use it. But
if you say this loaf is forbidden to me, forbidden is more
generic and global. So even though other people could eat it, you
are forbidden in any type of benefit, even the benefit of using
it for an עירוב. eiruv. Now this raises an interesting question that
תוספות Tosafos says, which is, according to a major camp in the
גמרא, Gemara a major position in the גמרא, Gemara you can only
make an עירוב תחומין eiruv techumin with דבר מצוה, dvar mitzvah, not
with דבר רשות. dvar reshut. So whatever happened to the idea of
מצוות לאו להנות ניתנו, mitzvot lav lehanot nitnu, right? So you're not
getting הנאה hana'ah because it's for the sake of the מצוה. mitzvah.
Although it's a little bit not the standard מצוות לאו להנות ניתנו.
mitzvot lav lehanot nitnu. The standard מצוות לאו להנות ניתנו mitzvot lav
lehanot nitnu to me means the reward I get for being מקיים
mekayeim the מצוה mitzvah doesn't count as הנאה. hana'ah. Here although I'm
doing it for the purpose of the מצוה, mitzvah, I am getting
other benefits from it. I'm getting the practical allowance to travel a
particular distance. Okay, so that's an interesting question of would you put
this in the category of מצוות לאו להנות ניתנו. mitzvot lav lehanot
nitnu. But that's the way רש״י Rashi understands the difference, that in
one case it's about eating, the other case is more broader about
any benefit, which includes the benefit of using it for an עירוב.
eiruv. Now we'll see where, I'll give you another way of thinking
about it in a minute, but let's see where the גמרא Gemara
goes with it.
So let's say, just take this thing, let's think of this for
a second, take things to an extreme example, right? חזיר. chazir. None
of us can eat it, but somebody else can.
In most of the world can. Yeah, presumably it goes by Jews.
Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, how about somebody who's פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh and needs to
eat טריף trayf food? Okay, anyways the גמרא Gemara says like this:
מיתיבי. meitivi. הנודר
מן הכיכר, hanoder min hakikar, if somebody takes a vow not to
eat from a loaf of bread, מערבין לו בה, mearvin lo bah,
you can use it for an עירוב. eiruv. And that seems to
be the case that you said this loaf is forbidden. Seems like
a generic case. מאי לאו דאמר עלי, mai lav deamar alai, it's
forbidden to me? לא, דאמר זו. lo, deamar zo. No, you say
I won't eat this one, but you don't generically make it forbidden.
Now the גמרא Gemara actually said לא דאמר לא אוכל, lo deamar
lo ochel, since the fundamental difference is eat versus generic. But anyway
this is the way רש״י Rashi understands it. No, the case is
you said you won't eat it. What, isn't that temporary generally
speaking?
You mean you can eat
it this week but ultimately you'll be...
yeah, but no, you could have taken a permanent one. You could,
you could say I'll never eat of this loaf, particularly not all
bread, this particular loaf is always forbidden to me.
Could you make an עירוב תחומין eiruv techumin on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur when you can't eat? We'll get to that.
הכא נמי מסתברא, hacha nami mistavra, this makes sense. תני סיפא. tani
seifa. אימתי, בזמן שאמר שבועה שלא אטעמנו. eimatai, bizman sheamar shebu'ah shelo
et'amenu.
The end of that ברייתא braita says,
when is it okay? If you say a שבועה shevuah that I
won't taste it. So specifically it's about taste.
אבל אמר עלי מאי? aval amar alai mai?
So if you just said it generically, it's forbidden to me without
being specific about eating or tasting, מאי, mai, what would you say?
הכי נמי דאין מערבין לו בה? hachi nami de'ein mearvin lo bah?
That you couldn't use it? אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true,
אדקתני כיכר זו הקדש אין מערבין לו בה, adkatani kikar zo hekdesh
ein mearvin lo bah, why does the end of that ברייתא braita
say that if you say this loaf is הקדש, hekdesh, you actually
sanctify it, you can't use it, which by the way makes sense
because nobody can eat it if it's הקדש. hekdesh. So according to
you, לפי שאין מערבין בהקדשות, lefi she'ein mearvin behekdeshot, because you can't
use הקדש hekdesh for an עירוב, eiruv, ליפלוג וליתני בדידי. liflog ulitni
bididi. You could have made a more subtle distinction. You could have
distinguished even the שבועה shevuah נדר neder cases. במה
דברים אמורים, bameh dvarim amurim, when can you use it? דאמר זו,
deamar zo, when you say I won't eat or taste this. אבל
אמר עלי, aval amar alai, if you generically said it's forbidden to
you, אין מערבין לו בה, ein mearvin lo bah, then you can't
use it. So how come it goes all the way to הקדש?
hekdesh? It sounds like anything less than הקדש hekdesh would be okay.
אמר לך רב הונא, Amar lach Rav Huna, רב הונא Rav Huna
would say back to you, אלא מאי, ela mai, what do you
want to say? כל היכא דאמר עלי מערבין, kol heicha deamar alai
mearvin, that when you say עלי alai you could be doing an
עירוב? eiruv? So קשיא רישא, kashya reisha, so it's still a contradiction
to the רישא reisha because the רישא reisha says that it's only
when you say שלא אטעמנו, shelo et'amenu, which sounds like that's the
only case that's a problem. So the ברייתא braisa apparently goes to
two extremes. The beginning says when it's a problem, when you say
שלא אטעמנו. shelo et'amenu. When is it good when you say שלא
אטעמנו? shelo et'amenu? When is it a problem when it's הקדש? hekdesh?
So what about all the middle cases that aren't just אטעמנו at'amenu
or הקדש hekdesh like you say generically it's forbidden to me? So
the גמרא Gemara says קשיא
רישא. kashya reisha. The גמרא Gemara says that I would have gotten
out. חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. chasorei mechasra vehachi katani. That I would
have said it's missing some words and here's how it should be
read. הנודר מן הכיכר מערבין לו בה, hanoder min hakikar mearvin lo
bah, that if you make a vow not to eat from a
loaf, you can use it for an עירוב. eiruv. ואפילו אמר עלי,
va'afilu amar alai, and even if you say עלי alai in the
generic way,
נעשה כמו שלא אטעמנו. na'aseh kemo shelo et'amenu. It's as if you
said I won't taste in the more narrow way, that would have
been okay. Any and everything is okay until you say הקדש. hekdesh.
So if it was the if we could I could read the
ברייתא braisa that says everything is good unless you say הקדש. hekdesh.
בכל מקום קשיא לרב הונא Bechol makom kasha l'Rav Huna but for
רב הונא Rav Huna it's difficult. Why did it say הקדש hekdesh
was the problem, there's something earlier that's a problem when you just
say you know עלי. alai. So the גמרא Gemara says alright that
ברייתא braisa is a problem but הא דאמר כרבי אליעזר ha d'amar
k'Rabbi Eliezer there's a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer ברייתא braisa: that goes
like him דתניא d'tanya we taught in a ברייתא: braisa רבי אליעזר
אומר שבועה שלא אוכל כיכר זו מערבין לו בה. Rabbi Eliezer omer
shvua shelo ochal kikar zo maarvin lo bah. If you say a
שבועה shvua that you won't eat this loaf you can use it
for an עירוב. eruv. כיכר זו עלי, Kikar zo alai, this loaf
is forbidden to me, אין מערבין לו בה. ain maarvin lo bah.
You cannot use it. So we have רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that
exactly makes that distinction about if I won't eat it it's okay,
it's forbidden to me generically it's no good as opposed to the
ברייתא braisa. that said the only problem is when you actually make
it הקדש hekdesh and then it becomes forbidden to everyone. So now
the גמרא Gemara says ומי אמר רבי אליעזר הכי umi amar Rabbi
Eliezer hachi did רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer really say this distinction? ותניא
זה הכלל Ve'tanya zeh haklal this is the principle אדם אוסר עצמו
באוכל מערבין לו בה adam oser atzmo be'ochel maarvin lo bah if
a person makes himself forbidden to food you can use it for
an עירוב. eruv. אוכל
הנאסר לו לאדם Ochel hanesar lo l'adam if the food is forbidden
so presumably that means not just I won't eat it but more
generically forbidden אין מערבין לו בה ain maarvin lo bah you can't
use it which by the way is exactly what we just said
is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and is the position of רב הונא
Rav Huna this distinction.
But that was the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. רבי אליעזר אומר כיכר
זו עלי מערבין לו בה כיכר זו הקדש אין מערבין לו בה.
Rabbi Eliezer omer kikar zo alai maarvin lo bah kikar zo hekdesh
ain maarvin lo bah. He says like the previous ברייתא. braisa He
says that it's totally okay until you make it
הקדש hekdesh לפי שאין מערבין בהקדש lefi she'ain maarvin b'hekdesh you don't
use הקדש. hekdesh. הא תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי אליעזר Ha trei tanna'ei
aliba d'Rabbi Eliezer fine there's a debate what רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer
position is. So basically what you have here is different positions in
the ברייתות braisas of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and of the ברייתות
braisas according to one whether you say שבועה shvua whether you say
נדר שלא אטעמנו neder shelo et'amenu כיכר זו עלי kikar zo alai
everything is okay because somebody else can eat it okay and until
you make it הקדש hekdesh that nobody can eat it and it
wouldn't be considered like an איסור הנאה issur hana'ah because it's a
מצוה מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו. mitzvah mitzvos lav l'henos nitnu. And then
you have the position of according to one ברייתא braisa or one
version of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that makes a distinction between saying
זו zo and עלי. alai. זו Zo it's okay עלי alai it's
no good what's the difference? So רש"י Rashi says the difference is
that עלי alai means זו zo is I won't eat it I
won't taste it it's more specific. עלי Alai is more generic and
therefore using it for an עירוב eruv is a type of a
forbidden benefit when you make it generically. I should point out and
תוספות Tosafos makes this point that there's another hidden difference going on
here which is interesting for those who learn שבועות Shvuos and נדרים
Nedarim which is and it really was almost stated explicitly in this
last ברייתא braisa we read which is the difference between whether you
focus on the person or the object. A שבועה shvua focuses on
the person. I won't eat it. I won't taste it. I won't
derive benefit. A נדר neder focuses on the object. כיכר זו עלי
Kikar zo alai this thing is forbidden to me the object is
forbidden not I'm forbidden the object is like a forbidden food okay
and that seems in the ברייתא to be more what's emphasized as
the difference rather than if you use the word eat versus generically
forbidden. The emphasis really more was am I making myself forbidden then
the food is still כשר. kosher. Okay maybe I can't eat it
but it's still כשר. kosher. If I say the food is forbidden
then the food is more like טריפה treif food okay then that
becomes more problematic. So that's a different way of understanding the issue
נדר neder versus שבועה shvua rather than a generic prohibition as opposed
to specifically about eating or tasting.
Okay so you see that the food is forbidden then you can't
according to one position according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer according to
one version.
He can't use the wine the food is forbidden to him right?
So the difference was so a that's debated סומכוס Sumchus number one
that some say when it is forbidden to other people no good
and b according to תוספות sort of says that would be similar
to הקדש hekdesh so that's even getting close to the הקדש hekdesh
category because verbally you are turning it into a forbidden object so
it might be an expansion of the הקדש hekdesh category even though
technically you're right other people could eat it. Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this מערבין לנזיר ביין maarvin l'nazir b'yayin back
to עירוב. eruv. And this is the issue we've been talking about
which is the subjective versus you know universal and so on for
according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma even if you can't eat
the food if somebody else can. A נזיר nazir can do wine
because other people can eat
it. מתניתין דלא כבית שמאי Masnisin d'lo k'Beis Shammai our משנה mishnah
is not like בית שמאי Beis Shammai דתניא בית שמאי אומרים אין
מערבין לנזיר ביין ולישראל בתרומה d'tanya Beis Shammai omrim ain maarvin l'nazir
b'yayin u'l'Yisrael b'trumah you cannot do it for a נזיר nazir for
wine and a ישראל in תרומה. truma? בית הלל אומרים מערבין לנזיר
ביין ולישראל בתרומה Beis Hillel omrim maarvin l'nazir b'yayin u'l'Yisrael b'trumah fine
so our משנה mishnah is בית הלל Beis Hillel no חידוש. אמרו
להם בית הלל לבית שמאי Amru lahem Beis Hillel l'Beis Shammai בית
הלל Beis Hillel said to בית שמאי: Beis Shammai: אי אתם מודים
Iy atem modim don't you agree
שמערבין לגדול ביום הכיפורים shemaarvin l'gadol b'Yom HaKippurim there you go Mike
that for an adult on יום כיפור Yom Kippur you can do
an עירוב eruv even though he can't eat it? So no one
can eat it which is even more fascinating right? So and it's
not גזירה שוה gezeirah shava but the point is that it's fit
food that's fit to be eaten by Jews at a different time
okay and even that's okay. So אמרו להם אבל amru lahem aval
they said yes אבל aval in early mishnaic idiom means like yes
I can see the point. So אמר להם amar lahem כשם שמערבין
לגדול ביום הכיפורים kesheim shemaarvin l'gadol b'Yom HaKippurim same way you can
do it for an adult on יום כיפור Yom Kippur כך מערבין
לנזיר ביין kach maarvin l'nazir b'yayin you could do it for a
נזיר nazir for wine because a נזיר nazir somebody else could eat
it.
There at least a minute before right before it became Yom Kippur
it was fit to be eaten by the person that laid it
and the whole idea is that where the food is is where
you began your Shabbos or began your Yom Kippur. So that's okay.
הכא ליכא סעודה ראויה
מבעוד יום. Hacha leka seudah re'uyah mibode yom. Here from the you
know here it wasn't fit the day before so the fact that
theoretically somebody could eat it is not relevant to me. Now the
Gemara says כמאן Keman who is this idea of that Beit Shammai
and Beit Hillel are arguing about the wine for a Nazir going
like? דלא כחנניה D'lo k'Chananya not like Chananya. דתניא Detanya we taught
in a Baraita חנניה אומר Chananya omer כל עצמן של בית שמאי
לא היו מודים בעירוב kol atzman shel Beit Shammai lo hayu modim
b'eruv Beit Shammai like categorically would not agree to the whole idea
of an eruv. עד Ad meaning just what a loaf of bread
or food or whatever that's gonna do it? No. You can't say
you started Shabbos just because you had a little food there. עד
Ad if you want to say you started Shabbos here you know
what you gotta do? יוציא מטתו וכל כלי תשמישו לשם. Yotzi mitato
v'chol klei tashmisho l'sham. Right. So so you
gotta bring your bed out there and your clothes and everything, your
chair, your whole house out there if you want to say that's
where you started. So anyway clearly according to the version that the
most they debated with was wine for a Nazir that's not that
position. So כמאן אזלא הא דתניא Keman azla ha detanya who's it
going like that which we learned in the Baraita? עירב בשחורים לא
יצא בלבנים Eirev b'shchorim lo yeitzei b'levanim if you made your eruv
and you were wearing black clothes when you went out there cuz
one way you can make an eruv is just physically being in
the place without putting the bread there just staying being in that
place when it becomes Shabbos. So if you were if you did
that and you were wearing black clothes then when you go out
the next day don't be wearing white clothes. בלבנים נחזי B'levanim nechezei
לא יצא בשחורים. lo yatza b'shchorim. So who don't go out so
who's that going like? What does it what's the sense of that?
So כמאן אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק חנניה היא ואליבא דבית שמאי.
Keman amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak Chananya hi v'aliba d'Beit Shammai. It's
Chananya according to Beit Shammai which basically means that it's a little
strange what they even think it means but somehow you don't have
if you want to go out the next day in different clothes
obviously you didn't have all of your כלי תשמישו klei tashmisho there
cuz you had to change your clothes. So so the Gemara says
וחנניה בשחורים הוא דלא יצא בלבנים יצא? u'Chananya b'shchorim hu d'lo yatza
b'levanim yatza? But one minute if that's true then you can't even
go out with white clothes because you basically are saying that you
didn't have all your clothes there. והא אמר עד שיצא מטתו וכלי
תשמישו לשם? v'ha amar ad she'yeitzei mitato u'klei tashmisho l'sham? So as
long as you didn't have all your clothes there it doesn't matter
what you want to wear the next day. So the Gemara says
הכי קאמר Hachi ka'amar this is what it means. עירב בלבנים והוצרך
לשחורים Eirev b'levanim v'hutzrach l'shchorim if you did it in white clothes
and then you realize that you needed black clothes אף בלבנים לא
יצא af b'levanim lo yatza then you can't even go out with
your white clothes. כמאן אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק חנניה היא ואליבא
דבית שמאי Keman amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak Chananya hi v'aliba d'Beit
Shammai that you need it's Chananya's version of Beit Shammai that you
need everything you're going to need for Shabbos to have been at
the place you began your eruv. So if you ever are concerned
you know if you feel sometimes that a certain halacha is too
machmir or whatever you should appreciate that our basic system is a
Beit Hillel system and there were a lot more machmir alternatives that
we have rejected along the way. Alright now סומכוס אומר Sumchus omer
now we get to this interesting debate of whether it's enough that
it could be eaten by someone else because סומכוס Sumchus says no
it's a Yisrael cannot do it for trumah it needs to be
חולין. chullin. So סומכוס Sumchus is the one that says it has
to be eat be able to be eaten by the person himself.
So now the Gemara has a question why does he only argue
about the trumah case? ואילו לנזיר ביין לא פליגי V'ilu l'Nazir b'yayin
lo pligi he doesn't disagree about the Nazir and the wine. Why
is that any different? I mean there also it could be eaten
by other people why there does he concede that that's okay? So
מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama why is a Nazir why can a Nazir
use wine according to Sumchus? אפשר דמיתשיל אניזירותיה Efshar d'mitschil a'nezirutei
because a Nazir can ask you know can get heter on you
know can go to a can do like התרת נדרים. hatarat nedarim.
He can go to a חכם chacham and being a Nazir is
only something that comes from a verbal you know statement it's like
a נדר neder it's based on your sort of verbal thing you
will be a Nazir you've turned yourself into a Nazir. So the
same way you could do a התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim you could
do a heter on the נזירות. nezirut. So in theory this wine
is drinkable by you because you could always undo the נזירות nezirut
like during בין השמשות bein hashmaishos even בין השמשות bein hashmaishos you
know which is sort of when the eruv takes place because even
though as Tosfos points out you're not supposed to do התרת נדרים
hatarat nedarim on Shabbos you're allowed to do it לצורך שבת. l'tzorech
Shabbos. So here it's לצורך שבת l'tzorech Shabbos because he needs the
wine in order to make the eruv and so on. So anyway
in theory בין השמשות bein hashmaishos you would be allowed to do
it and therefore it's in theory fit for you. Okay so the
Gemara says
it's actually an interesting question is it enough לצורך שבת l'tzorech Shabbos
that you want to use the eruv or would it have to
be לצורך שבת l'tzorech Shabbos that you actually like want to make
kiddush on wine on Shabbos? But okay anyway but in theory you
could find a reason to do a התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim on
the נזירות nezirut and therefore in theory it's fit for you. אי
הכי Ei hachi if that's what you're saying because in theory it's
fit תרומה נמי trumah nami so trumah also is in theory fit
for you. How? You can't become a כהן kohen. but here's how
it could be fit. אפשר דמיתשיל עלויה Efshar d'mitschil alei because a
trumah is also the status of grain as trumah is also made
by a verbal act. Verbal acts that change status are basically called
הפלאה haflaah because the תורה Torah says כי יפלא ki yafli when
you enunciate לנדור נדר נזיר. lindor neder nazir. So classic act is
a שבועה shvua and a נדר, neder, but it's also הקדש, hekdesh,
making something תרומות ומעשרות, trumos umasros, making yourself a נזיר, nazir, all
these things are types of הפלאה. haflaah. And all these types of
things can be undone by doing a התרת נדרים. heter nedarim. So
the גמרא Gemara says so תרומה truma also could be fit for
you. You can undo תרומה? truma, Yep, you could undo it until
you've given it to a כהן. kohen Then it becomes it becomes
actually property of the כהן. But until then it's just a vow.
I mean it's just a sort of status.
Okay. Even if you've eaten food already then?
No. Okay. אי משתילא, Ei mishtayla, if you had a התר heter
on it, הדר לטבלא, hadra letivla, then it still wouldn't be fit
because then it would become טבל, tevel, right? Because you took the
תרומה truma from grain that was טבל. tevel. So if it stops
being תרומה, truma. then the grain goes back to being טבל. tevel.
So you're stuck! So the גמרא says, oh wait wait wait, no
no no, here's what you could do it this way. וליפרשיה ממקום
אחר. Velifrashiah mimakom acher. In theory you could undo the תרומה truma
and in theory all this בין השמשות, bein hashmashos, you could go
ahead and be מפריש mafrish תרומות ומעשרות trumos umasros again using other
grain. So the גמרא says no. לא נחשדו חברים לתרום שלא מן
המוקף. Lo nechshdu chaverim litrom shelo min hamukaf. The other stuff you
would take from would be the stuff back in your house. That
would be the new תרומה. truma But then the new תרומה truma
would not be in the same pile. מוקף mukaf is like brought
together, you know, connected, like in the, you know, together with the
stuff that you're trying to take it on. And so even though
technically that works, you're not supposed to take תרומה truma unless all
the grain is in the same pile, is all together. So here
you can't say I'll make that מותר mutar by taking תרומה truma,
on the stuff back in my house. You you know, if you're
a חבר, chaver, right? Which is, you know, somebody who's very מקפיד
makpid on this type of stuff, you wouldn't do it. So we're
not going to say in theory you could do something that you
shouldn't be doing. So the גמרא says one minute. וליפרשיה מיניה וביה.
Velifrashiah minei uvei. So what? So say I'm undoing the תרומה truma.
and a little part of that מצה matzah that I have over
there for my עירוב eiruv should you know only some of it
should be the תרומה, truma. not the rest of it. So the
גמרא says דלית ביה שיעורא. Deleis bei shiura. There's not enough. There's
only an exact amount of שתי סעודות shtei seudos worth. And if
you try to take תרומות ומעשרות, trumos umasros, you want to turn
it back into טבל tevel and take תרומות ומעשרות trumos umasros from
it, you won't be left with enough that's שתי סעודות shtei seudos
worth. So the גמרא says ומאי פסקא? Umai piska? What makes you
think that it's like definitely exactly that case? I mean if סומכוס
Sumchus is saying you can only do it by the נזיר nazir
and not by this, it doesn't mean that there's some cases you
can't do it by the תרומה. truma, It sounds like categorically you
can't do it by the תרומה. truma And I've just given you
a case where it would be possible. You undo the תרומה, truma
you take it again from within the same thing, dot dot dot.
Now you could just say that's too many theoreticals, right? In theory
I could undo the תרומה truma and in theory I could do
this and in theory I could do that. But that could be
that that's too far on a limb. But the גמרא has a
different answer why the תרומה is not good. So the גמרא says
אלא סומכוס סבר לה כרבנן. Ella Sumchus savar lah kerabbanan. Here's why
he says the difference between the יין תוסס yayin tasis and the
תרומה case. He holds like the רבנן. rabbanan. The רבנן rabbanan דאמרי,
de'amri, כל דבר שהוא משום שבות גזרו עליו בין השמשות. kol davar
shehu mishum shvus gazru alav bein hashmashos.
There's a debate between the רבנן, rabbanan, רבנן rabbanan and רבי, רבי
יהודה הנשיא, Rebbi Yehuda HaNasi, that רבי יהודה הנשיא Rebbi Yehuda HaNasi
says that basically דרבננס derabbanan's are not אסור asur בין השמשות. bein
hashmashos. בין השמשות Bein hashmashos is only a ספק safek period. דרבננס
Derabbanan's are ספק. safek. So דרבננס derabbanan's are not אסור asur בין
השמשות. bein hashmashos. By the way, interestingly, we rule like רבי לדבר
מצוה. lidvar mitzvah. So it's a if it's ערב שבת erev Shabbos
בין השמשות bein hashmashos and you need to do a דרבנן and
it's לדבר מצוה, lidvar mitzvah, we actually rule that it's מותר. mutar.
But and same thing מוצאי שבת. motzai Shabbos. דבר מצוה Dvar mitzvah
בין השמשות bein hashmashos between שקיעה shkia and צאת, tzeis, לדבר מצוה
lidvar mitzvah we rule like רבי. Except that there are a number
of a good number of פוסקים poskim that say that that position
that things are מותר בין השמשות, mutar bein hashmashos, דרבננס derabbanan's are
מותר בין השמשות, mutar bein hashmashos, is overridden if you've already done
a קבלת שבת kabbalas Shabbos or before you've done הבדלה. havdalah. Because
then it's not just the objective period of בין השמשות, bein hashmashos,
you've designated it already as שבת. Shabbos. So it wouldn't work so
you'd have to find a circumstance where that would be the case.
Anyway, we'll see more about that. But let's see how that answers
סומכוס. Sumchus. So it says סומכוס Sumchus holds like the רבנן rabbanan
that you do not allow דרבננס derabbanan's בין השמשות. bein hashmashos.
And therefore what? And therefore being מפריש תרומה mafrish truma is an
איסור דרבנן. issur derabbanan. So you can't say that you could be
מפריש תרומה mafrish truma in theory right now because that's an איסור
דרבנן. issur derabbanan. Although undoing your נזירות nezirus and התרת נדרים heter
nedarim is also an איסור דרבנן. issur derabbanan. But that actually everybody
agrees is מותר לצורך שבת. mutar litzorech Shabbos. Whereas being מפריש תרומה
mafrish truma is not. Right? What's the one of the things you
say right right before it gets dark? עשרתם ערבתם הדליקו את הנר.
Issartem eiravtem hadliku es haner. So you have to do תרומות ומעשרות
trumos umasros on you know before בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. But so
therefore you cannot say in theory you could make this fit. But
in the נזיר, nazir, in theory you could do a התרת נדרים,
heter nedarim, that is מותר לצורך שבת. mutar litzorech Shabbos. Okay let's
just finish this point, get to the two dots. כמאן
אזלא הא דתנן? Keman azla ha detnan? Who's it going like that
which we learned in the משנה? Mishna? יש שאמרו הכל לפי מה
שהוא אדם. Yesh she'amru hakol lefi mah shehu adam. This gets a
little bit back to the
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר we talked about before. All the שיעורים shiurim
go based on a subjective standard. What type you know according to
you the particular person.
המוליך... Hamolich... Not all the שיעורים. shiurim. The following שיעור. shiur. מלוא
קומצו מנחה Meloi kumtzo mincha when he takes the מנחה mincha the
כהן takes a קומץ kometz a handbreadth. It goes by not a
generic קומץ, kometz, it goes by his קומץ. kometz. מלוא חפניו קטורת
Meloi chofnav ketores by יום כיפור Yom Kippur when the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol takes the two hand the two handfuls of the incense,
right, he does his handfuls, not some generic amount. And, that's his,
השותה מלוא לוגמיו ביום הכיפורים Ha-shoshe meloi lugmav b'Yom Ha-kippurim when you
by יום כיפור Yom Kippur the amount of liquid you cannot drink
is the amount that fills up a cheek. It goes by your
cheek, not by universal amount. ובמזון
שתי סעודות לעירוב U-vimazon shtei seudos l'eiruv and also for עירוב eiruv
it goes how much you would eat two meals not a generic
amount.
But what about that? What does the רעבתן rav atan thing?
Like it goes... What? What about that? The רעבתן rav atan gets
downgraded. I don't know. So כמאן, k'man, so who's this going like?
We'll get to that. אמר רב זירא סומכוס היא, Amar Rav Zeira
Sumchus hi, it's סומכוס, Sumchus, דאמר מאי דחזי ליה בעינן, d'amar mai
d'chazei lei bayinan, that you need food that's fit for you to
eat, not fit for other people to eat. So here too, it's
the same idea. Now of course this more is ר' שמעון בן
אלעזר Reb Shimon ben Elazar because it's more talking about amount. And
you go by the amount that you would eat, not the amount
that somebody else would eat. But the גמרא says it's also consistent
with סומכוס Sumchus who says the type of food. It has to
be the type of food you would eat, not the type of
food somebody else could eat. So the גמרא says לימא פליגי דר'
שמעון בן אלעזר, leima pligi d'Reb Shimon ben Elazar, now it's Michael's
question. But half of this disagrees with ר' שמעון Reb Shimon or
half of ר' שמעון בן אלעזר Reb Shimon ben Elazar disagrees with
this. דתניא ר' שמעון בן אלעזר אומר מערבין לחולה ולזקן כדי מזונו,
D'tanya Reb Shimon ben Elazar omer maarvin lachole u-lezaken k'dei mezonov, for
a חולה chole person or a זקן zaken, you go by their
food. So that part is going by a subjective amount. ולרעבתן בסעודה
בינונית של כל אדם, U-lerav atan b'seuda beinonis shel kol adam, but
if somebody is like particularly has a big appetite, you just go
by a generic. So excluding the חולה chole and the זקן, zaken
his general approach is you go by a generic amount. And here
it says you go by a subjective amount. So the גמרא says
no, תרגומא targuma חולה chole וזקן zaken where it says that you
go by subjective, it could be talking about the חולה chole and
זקן zaken, case. אבל רעבתן, Aval rav atan, somebody that's ravenous, בטלה
דעתו אצל כל אדם. batla da'ato eitzel kol adam. He is considered,
you know, you don't you don't pay attention to people that are
doing weird things. So because the point is the גמרא said ravenous,
it did not say meaning it might not be a קולא חומרא
kula chumra distinction. It might be a normal person of your in
your situation does not normally eat this amount of food. But if
somebody is like six foot six, and you know, and has a
and eats more than somebody that's a smaller person, maybe you would
go by that שיעור. shiur. So the same way you go by
a חולה chole and a זקן, the reason you don't go by
the ravenous person is because even for normal other people in his
situation would not be eating more than this amount. So it's not
that you go by everybody's particular things, you need to somewhat be
in a particular category. So is your category a growing teenage boy
or is your category a חולה chole person or a you know,
or until then it goes by your subjective.
But you can't use רעבתן?
rav atan? What? So anyway, so in the end the גמרא ends
that according to סומכוס Sumchus and ר' שמעון בן אלעזר, Reb Shimon
ben Elazar, you go by subjective standard in terms of quantity and
in terms of what you would eat. But the Rabbis at least
disagree in terms of the issue of what you would eat, it's
enough that it could be eaten by others. Do they also disagree
in terms of the issue of quantity? That's what we discussed before,
could be inconsistent in terms of looking at this subjective objective distinction.
Okay.